Janelle M. Garcia

Phone: 305-812-6634 E-Mail: smarthr.janelle@gmail.com

Profile

A Human Resources Business partner who is performance and outcome-driven with more than a decade of experience in the Human Resources field. I am a strategic and creative thinker, innovative problem solver, and decision maker who effectively balances the needs of employees with the mission of the organization. With my strong communication, interpersonal relations, mentoring, negotiation and organizational skills I will prove to be an asset to any organization.

CORE COMPETENCIES

- Benefits Administration
- Recruiting and Retention
- FLSA, FMLA, ADA
- Employee and Labor Relations
- Employee Champion
- Union Negotiations Rep. (ER)
- Conflict Resolution

- HR Compliance
- Information Management
- Project Management
- HRIS System Implementation
- Performance Management
- Employee Wellness

Experience

Human Resources Director, Behavioral Family Solutions

February 2018 - Present

Behavioral Family Solutions is a young ABA company with over 150 clients and 130 ABA providers.

- Implemented a recruitment strategy and successfully hired BCBA's to a company who only staffed licensed clinicians as Analysts. This was key in order to become approved to accept private insurance payers as well as deliver service excellence.
- Implemented recruitment and selection strategy to hire best in class providers.
- Strategized and executed the conversion of contractors to W2 employees which was not industry standard.
- Implemented systems of records for smoother operations.
- Currently involved in the migration to Central Reach.
- Spearheaded the implementation of going to a paperless model.
- Completed and implemented employee handbook.
- Implemented benefits package for recruitment and retention.
- Assisting in the launch of affiliate company to deliver 40 hour RBT training and preparation for board certification.
- Acted in a consultative role to ownership in the delivery of Human Resource related function.
- Developed roles and job descriptions to delineate accountabilities.
- Structured roles and established appropriate pay plans for office administration.
- Currently involved in launching the mental health day services program to accommodate clients with multiple needs/diagnosis.

Human Resources/Payroll Director, Warren Henry Auto Group.

May 2014- February 2018

- Managed a workforce of 400+ employees in four locations within the human resources and payroll functions with four direct reports.
- Reorganized the human resource function to meet current regulatory and compliance standards as well as best practices.
- Rebuilt the human resource department's infrastructure including updating processes and policies to be in compliance while ensuring flexibility and efficiency to meet the needs of departmental managers and executives of the organization.
- Re-branded the human resource/payroll department to strive for service excellence and serve as business partners to our internal customers by opening the lines of communications with management staff and the employee base by introducing the utilization and implementation of various tools/programs such as employee newsletters, health and wellness program and recognition.
- Restored employee and C-Suite trust in the HR department through customer service excellence, providing honest guidance and feedback, being transparent in communications, building relationships with all levels, and showing that HR has their best interest in mind when making decisions on benefits and wellness.
- Spearheaded a cross functional recruitment strategy to include initiative between HR and Marketing resources in order to increase brand awareness by attending various events like local and out-of-state job fairs, community fairs,

University fairs, and targeted recruitment of specialized positions; create social media presence; create core values to improve the communication of the employer value proposition; and identified key challenges of the current culture and proposed path to correction i.e. lack of communication/transparency and proposed open management concept to target millennial generation.

- Acted as a change-management agent of company culture by creating systems of accountability and increased communication effectiveness.
- Inventoried and audited various benefits available such as 401(K), voluntary benefits, health and welfare benefits, and providing better communication to drive participation.
- Strategized ways to increase participation of non-HCE's into the 401(K) plan to be able to pass annual ADP nondiscrimination testing resulting in company decision for employer match, and auto enrollment. Conducted RFP for
 new agent of record to decrease administrative costs to fund.
- Oversaw the filing of 5500's timely each year.
- Managed and oversaw the activities for open enrollment at multiple locations and successfully attained 95% participation.
- Implemented recordkeeping methods in preparation for the Affordable Care Act and audited plan to correct areas of non-compliance.
- Oversaw the planning of activities of the 2nd annual health and wellness fair and formulated a company-wide committee to increase participation, awareness, and inclusiveness.
- Under my direction, within six months of my tenure, conducted health insurance deduction audit and was successful in recovering over 35K in under deducted/miss-deducted health insurance funds.
- Implemented a leadership-training program to drive performance and development.
- Implemented a recruiting and a selection program and reduced turnover by 10% in the sales force.
- Successfully reduced unemployment claims by 90% by enforcing the progressive discipline procedure, implementing performance improvement plans (PIP), and making terminations a last resort 9as applicable) after all avenues have been exhausted and ensuring proper documentation is utilized through the discipline and termination process by management staff and contesting UC claims when appropriate.
- Worked on implementation of a corporate university to drive continuous development.
- Successfully implemented ADP payroll, performance management and other tools customary within the HR realm.
- Handled all employee relations matters to include guiding and coaching managers as to proper documentation for termination, performance improvement of staff, and all employee conflict resolution matters with a focus on balancing the company needs, maintaining flexibility, remaining consistent with policies and practices, and maintaining fairness and equity for the employee.
- Oversaw Payroll and Payroll Accounting functions, oversight of 401K and workers' compensation audits yearly.

Human Resources Director, City of Doral

Feb. 2013 – May 2014

- Reorganized and re-strategized the Human Resources department to position it as effective partners to the organization's operations leaders.
- Managed a workforce of 300+ employees with a Human Resource Department of three direct reports.
- Responsible for managing a very lean operating budget of approximately \$150K while implementing and maintaining HR programs.
- Re-negotiated training contracts to reduce costs by 36% while still maintaining quality standard of learning by finding other avenues and resources.
- Planned, organized and directed the activities of the Human Resources Department, including recruitment and selection, classification and compensation, employee benefits, health and safety, organizational development and training, payroll, labor relations, and risk management in the area of workers' compensation.
- Was responsible for all employee actions such as new hires, promotions, demotions, transfers, performance reviews, reclassifications, and terminations.
- Resolved disputes and responded to EEOC charges and other employee relations issues.
- Worked with the Information Technology department to implement an employee development program to address skill gaps and enhance employee training.
- Provided interpretation to directors and employees regarding employee policies and procedures.
- Was the direct point of contact to all benefits providers to provide employee census of plans chosen and to coordinate
 events to provide benefit education and info to employees.
- Supervised FMLA and workers' compensation cases in accordance with the City's policies and Florida Statute.
- Directed open enrollment activities to ensure compliance with Affordable Care Act.
- Administered benefits and resolved issues, made recommendations to Council and the City Manager on benefit providers at time of renewal.
- Conducted interviews for senior-level positions.
- Administered, designed, and directed workflows processes for new hire onboarding and new hire orientation.
- Supervised/managed payroll entries into the Kronos timekeeping system and compile reports.

- Identified issues and needs of all citywide staff.
- Oversaw monthly health and wellness initiatives and coordinated the annual employee health fair to promote wellness and minimize claims utilization through employee education efforts.
- Planned employee recognition efforts to boost morale.
- Oversaw the health fair committee.
- Conducted yearly customer service and diversity sensitivity training citywide.
- Created, amended and interpreted employee policies and procedures and provide direction to supervisory staff.
- Created a comprehensive internship program.
- Maintained employee records for all City staff in accordance with record retention schedule.
- Maintained partnerships and programs with outside approved vendors to enhance employee engagement and development such as Barry University.
- Managed projects for the implementation, design and configuration of the online recruiting system and workflow processes.
- Managed projects for the implementation of the Kronos digital time off request system and workflow processes.

Human Resources Coordinator/Supervisor, City of Doral

Sept. 2012 – Feb. 2013

This position carried many of the responsibilities of the previous HR Coordinator position with a focus on higher-level employee relations issues concerning the police department employees, direct supervision of the Workers' Compensation Clerk, and the second HR Coordinator. Promoted in February 2013 to Human resources Director.

Human Resources Coordinator, City of Doral

July 2010 – Sept. 2012

- Promoted to HR Coordinator/Supervisor in September 2012
- Oversaw all employee actions to ensure accurate employee profiles and records.
- Coordinated and conducted employee orientation to ensure proper integration of employee into organization culture.
- Identified and developed training and education of various newly implemented software such as Neogov recruiting software and Kronos time management software to ensure efficient transition and effective use.
- Implemented, tested and administered Kronos time off request and Neogov systems after conducting a needs assessment and proposal of business case to Council for approval.
- Created several monthly statistical reports using Microsoft Excel, such information was instrumental for annual budgets and several internal departmental projects such as dashboard reporting.
- Developed training to introduce new performance and outcome based evaluation system to the organization.
- Managed workers' compensation, short-term disability, and FMLA to ensure accurate reporting and timely benefits.

Human Resources Specialist, Carnival Cruise Lines

January 2008 – July 2010

- Administered corporate relocation packages for existing employees and new hires.
- Processed the onboarding of over 20+ new hires at a time.
- Processed employee actions, such as; promotions, transfers, demotions, reclassifications and title changes.
- Reviewed and processed all tuition reimbursement requests.
- Maintained direct contact with immigration attorneys regarding employees with sponsored visas.
- Maintained I9 records and posted labor condition applications.
- Responsible for new hire deadline timely submission into payroll.
- Project manager for the implementation of the digital I9 system and e-verify of all employees.
- Project manager for implementation of the ADP recruiting system.

Education

Masters of Science in Human Resource Management, Florida International University

December 2013

Bachelors of Science in Legal Studies, Barry University

December 2012

Affiliations/Memberships

- Society For Human Resource Management (SHRM)
- Greater Miami Society For Human Resource Management (GMSHRM)

Additional Skills

- Knowledge of Legistar, Laserfiche, Munis, People Trak, People Soft, Neogov, Lawson, Kronos, ADP Workforce Now, Central Reach, and many other Saas.
- Proficient in Microsoft Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Outlook
- Bilingual- Spanish
- Ability to understand, interpret, and apply rules and procedures
- Excellent written, analytical, verbal, and organizational skills
- Ability to maintain a healthy working relationship with employees of all levels
- Ability to make independent decisions and exercise authority
- Ability to collaborate and work in a team environment